Francesco Scala

PHD STUDENT IN QUANTUM MACHINE LEARNING

Pavia, Italy

□ (+39) 3406416189 | ■ francesco.scala01@ateneopv.it | ♠ Work page: fisica.unipv.it/personale/Persona.php?ID=591 | ♠ Personal page: fran-scala.github.io/ | ☑ fran-scala | ☐ fran-scala



Summary_

I'm an eager **third-year PhD student in Quantum Machine Learning** (QML) at University of Pavia, focusing on both classical and quantum machine learning. I bring **strong foundations** in state-of-the-art **theoretical aspects of QML** as well as **proficiency in numerical simulations** of quantum computing systems and QML algorithms. Thanks to my collegiate and representative of PhD students experience, I am used to interdisciplinary and challenging environments. Apart from the academic side, I'm an outgoing and active person enjoying sports, gardening and travelling.

Work Experience _____

FULL-TIME

Mar - May 2024 Reserach intern IBM Research

Zurich - Switzerland

Research internship focused on **overparametrization** of Quantum Neural Networks . My supervisors are Dr. **Ivano Tavernelli** and Dr. **Francesco Tacchino**, I closely work also with Dr. **Christa Zoufal**.

2021 - present

PhD in Quantum Machine Learning Università degli Studi di Pavia

Pavia – Italy

My research deals with **QML algorithms**, with special focus on **overparametrization** and **regularization** properties of **Quantum Neural Networks**. Part of my studies are also devoted to simulations of quantum computing platforms. My supervisor is Prof. **Dario Gerace**.

PART-TIME

Oct 2022-present Teaching assistant Università degli Studi di Pavia

Pavia - Italy

• Lectures on General Physics at the degree program in Chemistry and Pharmaceutical Technologies

Jul - Dec 2022

Intern QUANTUM COMPUTING LAB - CINECA

Casalecchio di Reno (BO) - Italy

• Benchmarking of **HPC infrastructures** for quantum computing and **QML applications** (Python)

Education

2019 - 2021 Master degree in Physics of Quantum Technologies Università degli Studi di Pavia

Pavia – Italy

Graduation date: 23-09-2021

Thesis: "Witnessing Entanglement by Quantum Neural Networks"

2016 - 2019 Bachelor degree in Physics Università degli Studi di Pavia

Pavia – Italy

Graduation date: 24-09-2019

Thesis: "Machine learning techniques applied to the quantum many-body problem"

Contributions: conferences, schools _____

Nov 2023 Quantum Techniques in Machine Learning (QTML) 2023 CERN Geneve - Switzerland

Talk: A General Approach to Dropout in Quantum Neural Networks

Oct 2023 Quantum Computing and Simulation Workshop Istituto Veneto Venezia - Italy

Poster: A General Approach to Dropout in Quantum Neural Networks

Aug 2023 Superconducting Qubits and Algorithms (SQA) Conference IQM QUANTUM COMPUTERS Munich - Germany

Poster: Symmetrizing Quantum Machine Learning for Quantum Field Theory

	International Conference on Ontice of Freitancia Confined Creatons II	
Jun 2023	International Conference on Optics of Excitons in Confined Systems Università del Talk: Quantum computing platform with polariton integrated circuits	SALENTO Lecce - Italy
		A
Nov 2022	Quantum Techniques in Machine Learning (QTML) 2022 UNIVERSITY FEDERICO II	Napoli - Italy
	Poster: Quantum variational learning for entanglement witnessing	
Ago - Sept 2022	VCQ & AppQlinfo SummerSchool 2022 Universität Wien	Wien - Austria
	Student Talk: Quantum variational learning for entanglement witnessing	
Jul 2022	World Congress On Computational Intelligence 2022 IEEE	Padova – Italy
	Talk: Quantum variational learning for entanglement witnessing	
Jun 2022	Quantum Computing Hard- and Software Summer School 2022 EPFL, ETH ZÜRICH	Lausanne - Switzerland
	Poster: Quantum variational learning for entanglement witnessing	
Extracurricular Activities		
Apr 2023 - presei	Technical-scientific Committee Member BeQuantum	Online - Italy
	Production of technical posts. General posts review.	
May 2023	1st Place ETH QUANTUM HACKATHON 2023 - IQM CHALLENGE	Zurich - Switzerland
	 Topic: Exploiting symmetries in Quantum Machine Learning Tasks: TicTacToe (given), Schwinger model (our proposal) [link] 	
Apr 2022 - Jul 20.	Mentee Quantum Open Source Foundation (QOSF)	Online
	 Implementation of Krylov module within tequila Python package [link] Mentor: Prof. Jakob Kottmann 	
2022 - 2023	Phd Student representative Università degli Studi di Pavia	Pavia - Italy
Jan 2022	2nd Place MIT IQUHACK 2022 - MICRSOFT/IONQ DIVISION	Online
	Topic: Quantum game with educational purposesBlackjack-inspired quantum game named QuHackJack [link]	
Skills_		
	 Programming: Python, C++(basic) Quantum programming: Pennylane (in combination with JAX), Qiskit, tequila, AWS Braket Soft skills: predisposition to interpersonal relationships, teamwork, quick learner, proactive, time management 	
Langua	ges	
	Italian: Native English: Level C1 French: Level A1	
Publica	tions	
F. Scala et al.	Adv. Quantum Tech. 2300220 A GENERAL APPROACH TO DROPOUT IN QUANTUM NEURAL NETWORKS	s 2023
F. Scala et al.	arXiv:2306.05072 Deterministic entangling gates with nonlinear quantum photonic interferon	METERS 2023 (In review)
J. Kottmann, F. Scala	arXiv:2302.10660 Compact Effective Basis Generation: Insights from Interpretable Circuit Des	sign 2023 (Acc. by JCTC)

F. Scala et al. | IEEE - IJCNN 2022 Proceedings Quantum variational Learning for entanglement witnessing

2022